Partridge mss., 1914-1979 LMC 2330
Lilly Library
Partridge mss.
1914-1966
Lilly Library
Partridge, Eric, 1894-1979
LMC 2330
11 Boxes 11 standard
52 bound
The Partridge mss., ca. 1914–1979, consist of the correspondence, notebooks, and drafts of the works of lexicographer, Eric Partridge, 1894–1979, perhaps best known for his dictionaries of slang and unconventional English.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Eric Partridge (1894-1979) was born February 6, 1894, in Poverty Bay, New Zealand, son of John Thomas (a farmer) and Ethel Annabella (Norris) Partridge. In 1907, the family moved to Brisbane, Australia where Partridge passed his school years graduating from the University of Queensland in 1921, after studying Classics, French and English. He received his B.Litt. (with first class honors) from Oxford University in 1923. Serving in the Australian infantry during World War I, he lived through the horror of the Gallipoli campaign in 1915. In 1925, Partridge married Agnes Dora Vye–Parmenter with whom he had one daughter, Rosemary Ethel Honeywood Mann. After teaching for two years as a university lecturer in Manchester and London, Partridge gave up a promising academic career to found the small London publishing house, Scholartis. The press was moderately successful until the Great Depression, when he was forced to take on work as a free–lance writer. He often commented that the Depression allowed him to discover his real love and talent for writing books.
Partridge wrote over forty books on the English language, including well–known works on etymology, slang, jargon, and clichés. He died on June 1, 1979 in Devon, England.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1965-1979
Scope and Contents
This collection is divided between correspondence, writings by Partridge, and writings by others. Correspondence is organized chronologically, writings are organized alphabetically. Larger works included in this collection are the Dictionary of Slang, 6th Edition, A Dictionary of the Underworld, and Origins:A Short Etymological Dictionary of Modern English.
Related Materials
See Partridge mss. II; Brown, A. mss.; Davidson mss.; Elliott, R. mss.; Pearse mss. also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
English language; Lexicography; Slang; Partridge, Eric, 1894-1979
- Correspondence
  - 1815-1899. (Box 1)
  - 1900-1925. (Box 1)
  - 1926-1928. (Box 1)
  - 1929. (Box 1)
  - 1930, Jan.-July. (Box 1)
  - 1930, Aug.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1931, Jan.-May. (Box 1)
  - 1931, June-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1932. (Box 1)
  - 1933. (Box 1)
  - 1934. (Box 1)
  - 1935. (Box 1)
  - 1936. (Box 1)
  - 1937, Jan-June. (Box 1)
  - 1937, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1938, Jan.-July. (Box 1)
  - 1938, Aug.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1939, Jan.-June. (Box 1)
  - 1939, July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1940, Jan.-July. (Box 1)
  - 1940, Aug.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1941. (Box 1)
  - 1942. (Box 1)
  - 1943. (Box 1)
  - 1944. (Box 1)
  - 1945. (Box 1)
  - 1946. (Box 1)
  - 1947. (Box 2)
  - 1948. (Box 2)
  - 1949. (Box 2)
  - 1950. (Box 2)
  - 1951. (Box 2)
  - 1952, Jan.-June. (Box 2)
  - 1952, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1953. (Box 2)
  - 1954, Jan.-June (Box 2)
  - 1954, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1955, Jan-Apr. (Box 2)
  - 1955, May-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1956. (Box 2)
  - 1957. (Box 2)
  - 1958. (Box 2)
  - 1959. (Box 2)
  - 1960. (Box 2)
  - 1961, Jan.-June. (Box 2)
  - 1961, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1962, Jan.-June. (Box 2)
  - 1962, July-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1963, Jan.-June. (Box 3)
  - 1963, July-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1964, Jan.-June. (Box 3)
  - 1964, July-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1965, Jan.-June. (Box 3)
  - 1965, July-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1966, Jan.-June. (Box 3)
  - 1966, July-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1967, Jan.-Mar. (Box 3)
  - 1967, Apr.-July. (Box 3)
  - 1967, Aug.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1968, Jan.-July. (Box 3)
  - 1968, Aug.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1969, Jan.-May. (Box 3)
  - 1969, June-Nov. (Box 3)
  - 1969, Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1970, Jan.-May 14. (Box 3)
  - 1970, May 15-Sept. 10. (Box 3)
  - 1970, Sept. 11-Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1971, Jan.-May. (Box 4)
  - 1971, June-Sept. 7. (Box 4)
  - 1971, Sept. 8-Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1972, Jan.-Mar. (Box 4)
  - 1972, Apr.-July. (Box 4)
  - 1972, Aug.-Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1973, Jan.-June. (Box 4)
  - 1973, July-Nov. (Box 4)
  - 1973, Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1974, Jan. (Box 4)
  - 1974, Feb. (Box 4)
  - 1974, Mar.-June. (Box 4)
  - 1974, July-Oct. (Box 4)
  - 1974, Nov.-Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Jan. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Feb. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Mar.-Apr. (Box 4)
  - 1975, May-July. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Aug. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Sept. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Oct. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Nov. (Box 4)
  - 1975, Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Jan. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Feb. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Mar. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Apr. (Box 4)
  - 1976, May-July. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Aug.-Oct. (Box 4)
  - 1976, Nov.-Dec. (Box 4)
  - 1977, Jan.-Feb. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Mar. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Apr. (Box 5)
  - 1977, May-June. (Box 5)
  - 1977, July. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Aug. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Sept. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Oct. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Nov. (Box 5)
  - 1977, Dec. (Box 5)
  - 1978, Jan. (Box 5)
  - 1978, Feb. (Box 5)
  - 1978, Mar. (Box 5)
  - 1978, Apr. (Box 6)
  - 1978, May. (Box 6)
  - 1978, June. (Box 6)
  - 1978, July. (Box 6)
  - 1978, Aug. (Box 6)
  - 1978, Sept. (Box 6)
  - 1978, Oct. (Box 6)
  - 1978, Nov. (Box 6)
  - 1978, Dec. (Box 6)
  - 1979, Jan. (Box 6)
  - 1979, Feb. (Box 6)
  - 1979, Mar. (Box 6)
- Writings
  - Beginnings of the Classic-Romantic Controversy in France., 1925-1926 (Box 7)
  - A Note on Tragedy and Epic., 1926 (Box 7)
  - Jack Lindsay., 1927 (Box 7)
  - The History of Words., 1959 (Box 7)
  - Comic Alphabets., 1961 (Box 7)
  - Bibliography of works written or edited by Partridge., 1965 (Box 7)
  - All Our Penguins go to College., 1965 (Box 7)
  - Usage and Abusage., 1965 (Box 7)
  - Dictionary of Slang, 6th Edition, 1965-1966
    - Addenda. (Box 8)
    - Pages 1-25 (Box 8)
    - Pages 26-50 (Box 8)
    - Pages 51-100 (Box 8)
    - Pages 101-200 (Box 8)
    - Pages 201-269 (Box 8)
    - Fair Copy, postcard to Mrs. Gerrood, 1966-03-1966-07 (Box 8)
    - Preliminary Page and A-D (Box 8)
    - E-H (Box 8)
    - I-M (Box 8)
    - N-R (Box 8)
    - S-Z (Box 8)
  - Encyclopedia Americana article on "Cockney" and "Colloquialism", 1967 (Box 8)
  - And The Men Have Something Too (Box 8)
  - A Dictionary of the Underworld, Third Ed.
    - Original Notes (Box 8)
    - Addena (Box 8)
    - 250-253 (Box 8)
  - N.D. John Honeywood, Private, T.D. (Box 8)
  - N.D. John Honeywood, Private, Carbon. (Box 8)
  - Notes from Slang Dictionary (Box 8)
  - Notes for The Story of Words (Box 8)
  - Story of Words Forward to Suffixes (Box 8)
  - Origins: A Short Etymological Dictionary of Modern English (Box 8)
    - Origins, 4th Edition. (Box 8)
    - Origins: Translation. (Box 8)
    - Elements.
    - A (Box 8)
    - B (Box 8)
    - C (Box 9)
    - D (Box 9)
    - E (Box 9)
    - F (Box 9)
    - G (Box 9)
    - H (Box 9)
    - I-K (Box 9)
    - L (Box 9)
    - M (Box 9)
    - N (Box 9)
    - O (Box 9)
    - P (Box 9)
    - Q-R (Box 9)
    - S (Box 9)
    - T (Box 9)
    - U (Box 9)
    - V (Box 9)
    - W-Z (Box 9)
  - The Quiet Life Late Draft
    - Book 1 (Box 9)
    - Book 2 (Box 9)
    - Book 3 (Box 9)
    - Book 4 (Box 9)
    - Book 5 (Box 9)
    - Full Draft (Box 9)
  - Lingo, 1936
    - 1-140 (Box 10)
    - 141-264 (Box 10)
    - 265-393 (Box 10)
    - Duplicate Sheets (Box 10)
  - Doom of Illium
    - Ch. 1-8 (Box 10)
    - Ch. 9-13 (Box 10)
    - Ch. 14-19 (Box 10)
    - Ch. 20-24 (Box 10)
    - Ch. 25-34 (Box 10)
  - A Semantic Dictionary (Box 10)
  - The 1762 Efflorescence of Poetics (Box 10)
  - Slang (Box 10)
  - Subjunctions in French Grammar (Box 10)
  - Words and their Beginnings, the Dictionary (Box 10)
- Other Works
  - Shakespeare's Bawdy (Box 10)
  - 1938, The Works of Shakespeare (Box 10)
- Handwritten Notebooks and Workbooks
  - C. C. and C.
    - Vol. I.
    - Vol. II.
    - Vol. III.
    - Vol. IV.
  - A Dictionary of the Underworld
    - Vol. I.
    - Vol. II.
    - Vol. III.
    - Vol. IV.
    - Vol. V.
    - Vol. VI.
    - Vol. VII.
    - Vol. VIII.
    - Vol. IX.
    - Vol X.
  - A First English Dictionary
    - Vol. I.
    - Vol. II.
    - Vol. III.
    - Vol. IV.
    - Vol. V.
    - Vol. VI.
    - Vol. VII.
    - Vol. VIII.
  - 18th Century English Romantic Poetry., 1922, June - Sept.
  - Chateaux en Espagne… No 1., 1922, Jan. - 1926, Mar.
  - Châteaux en Espagne… no. 2.
  - A Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English., 1966-1968
  - Elizabethan Plays. Cahier B., 1919-1920
  - Elizabethan Plays (1558-1642): summaries. Cahier T., 1920.
  - Elizabethan drama. Cahier W., 1920.
  - English Cahier no. 1., 1921, Sept. - Oct.
  - English Cahier no. 2., 1921, Oct. - Nov.
  - English Cahier no. 3., 1921, Dec. - 1922, Jan.
  - English Cahier no. 4., 1922, Jan. - Mar.
  - English Literature 1570-1660., 1925, Mar. - 1926, Mar.
  - English Literature 1660-1700., 1925, Sept - Nov.
  - English Plays 1500–1642, summaries. II., 1920.
  - First English Dictionary Vol. 5., n.d.
  - A First English Dictionary: Letter, 13 Apr. 1960 to Mrs. Garrood and notebook pages.
  - A First Etymological Dictionary for Young People and Other Beginners.
  - French Cahier no. 1., 1922, Mar - Apr.
  - French Cahier no. 2a., 1922, Apr - 1923, Dec.
  - French Cahier no. 2b., 1922, June - Nov.
  - French Cahier no. 2c., 1922, Nov. 1923, Nov.
  - French Cahier no. 3a., 1922, Sept. - 1923, Jan.
  - French Cahier no. 3b., 1923, Jan. - May.
  - French Influences on 19th-century English Lit. Cahier 1., 1924, Aug. - 1926, July.
  - French influences on 19th-century English Lit. Cahier 2., 1925, May - 1927, July.
  - French Influences on 19th-century English Lit. Cahier 3., 1927, Jan. - June.
  - French Influences on 19th-century English Lit. Cahier 4., 1926, Mar. - 1929, Jan.
  - The Gentle Art of Lexicography, n.d.
  - The History of Words., 1959.
  - Literary Theory… plus 19th-century criticism., 1926, Jan. - May.
  - Notes for Classics course… Queensland. Cahier L., 1914-1915.
  - Notes for honors courses in English and French at Queensland., 1920-1921.
  - Poems of Cuthbert Shaw and Thomas Russell., 1923, Oct. - 1924, Nov.
  - The Quiet Life. Draft. (bound)
  - Robert Eyres Landor: biographical and critical sketch., 1926, Aug. - Dec.
  - Robert Eyres Landor. Selections.
  - A Semantic Dictionary of (Modern) English., n.d.
  - A Semantic Dictionary of Modern English (folder), n.d.
  - Studies in 18th-century Literature. Cahier 1., 1927, Jan. - June.
  - Studies in 19th-Century Literature. Cahier 2., 1927.
  - Swift's polite conversation., n.d.
  - Workers Education Assocation. Cahier no. 1., 1921.
  - Workers Educational Association. Cahier no. 2., 1921.